<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands ioy, for the kings gratious proclamation for the banishing papists</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09120</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2988.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116764</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">69648656</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 69648656</idno>
            <idno type="VID">184920</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09120)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 184920)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2879:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands ioy, for the kings gratious proclamation for the banishing papists</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 17 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Bernard Alsop and Thomas Fawcet],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed MDCXL. [1640]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication data suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Peterborough Cathedral.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:184920:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ENGLANDS IOY, FOR THE KINGS GRATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Proclamation for the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing <hi>Papiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 KING. 18.21.</bibl>
               <p>How long hault yee betweene two opinions? If the Lord be God, then follow him, if Baall, then follow him.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 KING. 17.24,25.</bibl>
               <p>And the King of Aſſyria brought men from Babylon, and from Cuthagh, and from Ava, and from Hamath, and from Sepharvaim, and placed them in the Cities of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria, in ſtead of the Children of Iſrael, and they poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Samaria, and dwelt in the Cities thereof.</p>
               <p>And ſo it was at the beginning of their dwelling there, that they feared not the Lord: Therefore the Lord ſent Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons among them, which ſlew ſome of them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed M.DC.XL.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:184920:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:184920:2"/>
            <head>ENGLANDS IOY, for the KINGS gratious Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation for the baniſhing of Papiſts.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Confeſſe that Prayer is ſo forcible, that it openeth the gates of Heaven; and as you read, how the holy <hi>Ghoſt</hi> deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the Apoſtles, in the forme of fiery tongues, ſo through the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement of Prayer, all bleſſings ſpirituall and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall are let downe amongſt the children of God, like <hi>Peters</hi> ſheete. Who would not then aske to obtaine: ſeeke to finde: knocke to have it opened: and importune the father of mercy to have no deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, conſidering the Parable tells us, That the wicked Judge who neither feared God nor man, granted the widowes Petition to be delivered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her clamors, and her troubleſome attendancy: and thus are wee beholding to our God.</p>
            <p>But now, to make God beholding unto us, were a ſecret out of the Treaſure-houſe of heaven indeed, wherein I will be bold to tell you how you may be proficient, and invite you to wiſedomes ſchoole to learne a cunning, which the heart of the naturall man is uncapable of; and that is, to retribute thankes to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:184920:3"/> God, to give his glorious name the praiſe, to bee gratefull unto him, and to rejoyce in hymnes and ſpirituall Songs, when a benefit is imparted, and our ſoules are comforted.</p>
            <p>What a ſtory is the ſtory of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> being deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from <hi>Hamans</hi> cruelty and perſecution, for the purpoſe in hand. The Text ſaith; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heſter</hi> 9.17,18</note> That they reſted the ſame day, and made it a day of feaſting and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, a good day, and ſent portions and preſents one to another: but wherefore was all this? For ſaving their lives, and prevailing againſt their enemies.</p>
            <p>But, oh thou God of heaven! that rideſt vpon the wings of the wind, and holdeſt the reynes of the kingdomes of the world in thy hand, to let looſe or reſtraine at thy pleaſure. Thou knoweſt that we haue more cauſes to rejoyce and bee glad then the <hi>Iewes,</hi> in their <hi>Purim.</hi> For, if wee may compare the leſſe with the greater, they had but the preſervation of their bodies, and a ſlight tryumph againſt their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall enemies, we are in the way to ſave our ſoules and put our ſpirituall adverſaries to flight, the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> the <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>Devill</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What? Papiſtry to be ſuppreſſed? The Prieſts and Ieſuites to be baniſhed? And the Goſpell of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt to flouriſh? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalme</hi> 45.</note> My ſoule leapes for joy, and my heart is enditing a good matter, I ſpeake of the things which I haue made, touching the King; my tongue is the pen of a ready writer. Oh bleſſed be <hi>GOD</hi> for this alteration?</p>
            <p>Doth not <hi>Ieremy</hi> tell vs, that, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ieremy</hi> 31. <hi>Math.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>In Ramah there was a voyce heard, lamentation, and weeping, and great mourning, Rachell weeping for her children, and would
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:184920:3"/> not be comforted becauſe they were not.</hi> Did not al <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> wring their hands for ſorrow, and begin to mourne and be affrighted, when they ſaw the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſo arrogantly miſchievous, to inſult in every towne and ſhire, and mocke us to our faces, as if <hi>Sandolet</hi> and <hi>Tobiah</hi> were to ſcoffe and deride the <hi>Iewes,</hi> when <hi>Nehemiah</hi> came to re-edifie the Temple? And hath not <hi>God</hi> put into the Kings heart to dam vp this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undation, and to keepe the raging Sea within limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, that it doe not overflow the lower and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full grounds.</p>
            <p>Marke but the progreſſion of buſineſſe, tell it to your Children, and write it in the Phylacteries of your garments. Did not we determin ſome 16. years agoe to match with <hi>Spaine?</hi> And did not <hi>Spaine</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to overmatch us in the contract? Did he not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble an unmannerly and impudent gueſt, who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited to ſome neighbourly meeting, would not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come himſelf, but brought a whole rablement of Cormorants with him, ſo <hi>Spain</hi> muſt not only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition for a daughter, but the <hi>Papiſts</hi> through the kingdome have liberty of Conſcience, Maſſe in their houſes, Prieſts within their doores, penalties remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the Purſevants and Officers reſtrained from their privy ſearches, whereby the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour preſumed on his meritorious ſervice, &amp; ſome Papiſts triumphed, as if the wiſer ſort knew they were in the right. And was not this a fearefull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and who knowes with what ſtrength the ſtrong man would have encreaſed in keeping his poſſeſſion: ſo have the <hi>Papiſts</hi> done within theſe 2. or 3. yeares, and inſolently bragged of their great
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:184920:4"/> forces, and impudently threatned the utter over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of us all, eſpecially of our renowned City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But was this all? No, no, the ſeverall ſhiers of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> worſe then the <hi>Iewes</hi> that poyſoned the ſprings of ſweet <hi>water,</hi> in theſe dayes had malitious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments to corrupt the youth of the Countrey, and the <hi>Prieſts, Ieſuites</hi> and <hi>Fryers</hi> ranne from houſe to houſe, and made them all amazed with crying out; <hi>Great is Diana of the Epheſians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now <hi>Papiſtry</hi> ſhall be ſuppreſſed, and the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Ieſuites</hi> baniſhed. O bleſſed alteration! O bleſſed King! oh bleſſed Parliament! The <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours</hi> houſes were ſo many hives, to which the drones reſorted, who not onely fed vpon the hony of the Bees, but preſumed to kill and beate them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, which preſerved them: Thus theſe unconſtant people, not onely deſpiſed the Paſtors of their own <hi>Congregations,</hi> and under protection of the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative</hi> of Kings, railed on the Lord &amp; his annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: The Streets ſwarmed with ruffianly appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Prieſts</hi> in diſguiſed apparell, and <hi>Ieſuites</hi> in Courtly veſtments. And what did they? Not only watch the outward behaviour of men, and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the City, but tooke advantage of the weake, carnall Goſpeller, and ſet upon them with the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward glory of a viſible Church.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cathedrall</hi> of <hi>Paules</hi> had her walkes mingled with a number of <hi>peremptory</hi> and audacious <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> who not onely branded us for lukewarmneſſe and unjuſtifiable actions, but boaſted both of and in their diſputations, that they had put the true and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:184920:4"/> learned ſervants of <hi>God</hi> to ſilence, as if <hi>Sidchiah</hi> ſhould ſtrike <hi>Machiah</hi> on the face, and peremptorily aske him, when the Spirit of God departed from him, to be infuſed into ſuch an underling.</p>
            <p>The Court hath not onely every corner, but pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like walkes filled with <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and <hi>Hiſpaniolized tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poriſers.</hi> And what did they, appeare in ſeverall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed formes, and their corrupt hearts taught their tongues to vent forth blaſphemy, and notorious abuſes: For as you read how <hi>Ieremy</hi> was taken by his Enemies, and brought before the Princes and Prieſts, for weakning the hands of the men of warre, and danted their hearts that wiſhed well to the peace of <hi>Sion:</hi> So played theſe impoſturing ſpirits, charming all men with ſuch ſubtilties. What? the houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> to be checked, and the <hi>Emperour</hi> of <hi>Germany</hi> to be affronted?</p>
            <p>What? <hi>Spain</hi> to be threatned with warre, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſions of hoſtility? Who is able to cover the <hi>Vienna,</hi> as <hi>Xerxes</hi> once did the <hi>Helleſpont,</hi> with a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berleſſe, and invincible Armado, to ſet upon the Iland of <hi>Brittany</hi> as a Conquerour, and to make <hi>England</hi> to tremble with the multitude of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and yet dare you talke of warre and aſſiſting the Low-Countries? But now God be thanked, <hi>Papiſtry</hi> ſhall be ſuppreſſed, the Prieſts and Ieſuits baniſhed, and theſe mighty Buls of <hi>Baſhan</hi> either have their hornes ſawed off, or their chaps muſled, and what an alteration is heere?</p>
            <p>Oh let us then give thankes unto God, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe his mercy is beyond our apprehenſion, and his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:184920:5"/> benefits are <hi>Ocean</hi> in compariſon of our duty, or ſtanding poole of deſerving. And ſeeing the King is ſo gracious to looke upon us, like a faire moving Planet, in a conſpicuous <hi>Orbe,</hi> from whoſe influence can proceed nothing but ſweet preſages: Seeing our Parliament is ſo religiouſly Honourable, to ſound the foord of <hi>Spaines</hi> projects, and their countries ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard by colluſion, and halting betweene two opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; with the plummets of true Wiſedome, and zeale to the Goſpell of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> Seeing that they are ſo indulgent, and will not ſuffer either the wild Bore of the <hi>Forreſt</hi> to trample downe the hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; or little Foxes to deſtroy the <hi>Grapes,</hi> but are willing that <hi>Iehojadas</hi> filthy garments may be taken away, and a Crowne of pure Gold ſet upon his head, ſeeing the people are prepared to call and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten one another to goe vp to the Temple of the Lord; and rather then <hi>Ruben</hi> ſhall rayſe a heape of ſtones like an Altar, to put the people in feare of Idolatry, they are ready to arme with their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and examine how the matter ſtands, let every man exhilarat himſelfe, and cry out: <hi>Why art thou caſt downe O my ſoule, and why art thou diſquieted within me? hope thou in God, for I ſhall yet praiſe him, he is the health of my countenance, and my God:</hi> So then if <hi>Paplſtry</hi> ſhall be ſuppreſſed, the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Ieſuites</hi> baniſhed, and our enemies, both Forraine and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticke over-reached: let <hi>God</hi> have the glory, the Prince the honour, the Parliament the commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the people the comfort, the Country the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and every true hearted Chriſtian ſing <hi>Iopaean,</hi> and <hi>Epithalamions</hi> to <hi>Iehovah.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:184920:5"/>
            <p>Marke the difference betweene flouriſhing King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes through the bleſſing of reformation, and adviſe of good governours, and the fearefull diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Common-wealths, where <hi>irreligion</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct courſes over-maiſter: While the ambition of <hi>Athalia</hi> was predominant over her affection, and drive her head-long to all obſcenity &amp; tyranny, ſhe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted idolatry, ſhe neglected the houſe of God, ſhe defiled the Altar, ſhe deſtroyed the ſeed royall, ſhe uſurped the Diadem, and diſturbed the peace of <hi>Iuda</hi> and <hi>Iſrael:</hi> But when <hi>Iehoaſh</hi> was miraculouſly preſerved and inſtructed by <hi>Iehojada: Athalia</hi> is ſlaine: <hi>Iehoaſh</hi> doth that which is right in the ſight of God, the <hi>Prieſts</hi> repaire the Temple, the Altars are cleanſed, the Common wealth reformed, and the whole Country reſetled in order; and was not this a great alteration?</p>
            <p>In the ſtory of <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> and <hi>Ammon</hi> his Sonne, you ſhall finde theſe imputations of wickedneſſe caſt upon them by the holy Ghoſt: Hee did that which was evill in the ſight of the Lord, he lived after the abominations of the Heathen, he reared up Altars for <hi>Baal,</hi> he offered incenſe to the Hoſt of Heaven, he made his Sonnes paſſe through the fire, he uſed enchantments, obſerved times, and dealt with familiar ſpirits, and wrought much wickednes before the Lord: But when <hi>Ioſiah</hi> came to raigne, and was inſtructed how? he feared God, and lived uprightly, he cleanſed and repaired the Temple: he commanded the booke of God to be read, he rent his cloathes, as ſtrucken with compunction of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:184920:6"/> ſoule, he made a covenant with God to obſerve his teſtimonies, he put downe all the Offices of <hi>Baal,</hi> and the groves dedicated unto him: He ſlew his <hi>Prieſts,</hi> he ſolemnized the <hi>Paſſeover,</hi> and he perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the words of the Law, which were written in the Booke; and was not this a great alteration?</p>
            <p>Thus it is betweene the government of <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> eſpecially the contrariety of Religion, and diverſity of ſerving God, betweene <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants:</hi> the <hi>Papiſts</hi> both in <hi>Spaine</hi> and in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> commit blaſphemous idolatry, are polluted with inceſts and fornication; <hi>derogate from the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God,</hi> to attribute adoration to creatures, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifieth himſelfe in the <hi>Labyrinth</hi> of aequivocation: Diſſemble with God, their owne ſoules, and all that deale with them, care not by what meanes, or <hi>treachery they compaſſe their owne ends,</hi> deny Chriſts preſence in Heaven, a maine article of Faith, exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate the power of the God-head, by allowing a deity to Creatures, and invocation to Divells<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Firſt, they have made many Saints that are paſſed downe to Hell. Allow of <hi>murther,</hi> and monſtrous impiety: and in a word, are poyſoned with the dregs of abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, wherewith the whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> hath filled her cup.</p>
            <p>The true Proteſtant and zealous Chriſtian allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth God the preheminence of all adoration, will by no meanes blaſpheme with idolatrous exorciſmes, deteſteth <hi>whoredome,</hi> and all inceſtuous <hi>Leproſie,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the participiation of Gods glory to <hi>murther,</hi> ſimply and plainly contriveth his affaires, and kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth his word, though it be to his owne hinderance,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:184920:6"/> intermeddles not with matters of ſtate, except he be called to place of eminency, is with <hi>Anna</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Temple, and continually rejoyceth in the converſation of Gods ſervants, and maketh the Church the ſanctuary of his ſoule, <hi>in a word, is ruled by the directory of Gods word,</hi> and neither dare abuſe the Majeſty of Princes by inter jecting a Jealouſie and ſuſpition betweene the <hi>Prince</hi> and the <hi>Subject,</hi> nor runne away with the deceit of his owne heart, <hi>in preſuming to be more holy then his brethren, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judging others either maliciouſly, or fooliſhly.</hi> And is not this a great alteration? And is not this cauſe enough to induce us to thanke God, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his mercy and kindneſſe, that our King and Parliament would goe and buy eye-ſalve without money, <hi>perſpicuouſly to looke into the enormities of the Church and Common wealth,</hi> and not onely with <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah,</hi> to abridge the extreamity of uſury: compell a relaxation of debts and oppreſſion, keepe and ſanctifie the Sabbath, drive the Marchants and Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of meate out of the City, and at laſt put away their idolatrous wives: but alſo will not ſuffer the <hi>Ammonites</hi> and <hi>Moabites</hi> to come into Gods Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but enforce them to baniſhment out of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi> For as you read how <hi>Iacob</hi> after his return from <hi>Laban</hi> cleanſed his houſe of the idols: ſo did <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> in deſpite of <hi>Eliaſhib</hi> the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> who had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyed himſelfe to <hi>Tobiah</hi> a ſtranger and idolater, put him from his lodging, and caſt out all the ſnuffe out of his chamber, which in the text is likewiſe called cleanſing, and thus thankes be to God, our great <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:184920:7"/> dealt with the Papiſts, he hath not onely thought them as prickes and thornes in the ſides of good <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> but now found them as noy ſome and infectious weedes in the Common wealth, to choake and eate up the ſweete Flowers, and ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing graſſe; and thus hath the <hi>Church</hi> of God exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple enough in <hi>Scripture</hi> to be an enemy to Gods enemies, and fall to <hi>reformation</hi> with courage and magnanimity.</p>
            <p>Shall ſuch a man as I flye (ſaith <hi>Nehemiah</hi>) ſhall ſuch a King as I (ſaith King <hi>Charles</hi>) that have been trayned up from my infancy to deny <hi>Popery,</hi> and ſuffer my Kingdome of <hi>great Britaine,</hi> the very <hi>nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery</hi> of zealous <hi>profeſſors,</hi> and <hi>mirrour</hi> of purity and piety, to be defiled and contaminated with the poyſon of ſuperſtition, and now I have recollected my ſelf, ſhall I give way to rotten and filthy policy to eat upon the heart of true Religion, or ſuffer pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate ends to thicken themſelves, like ſome obſcure and dangerous cloud, to ſtand as an interpoſition betweene the Sunny ſplendor of Gods word, and the faire progreſſe of government? No, No: J will now be my ſelfe, and therefore if either the Pope, or <hi>Spain</hi> deride me with <hi>Michol</hi> for dancing before the Arke, and bringing it into Gods houſe: I will anſwere with <hi>David,</hi> I will yet bee more vile and zealous for the Lord; and as he told his wife; that therefore God had taken the Kingdome from her Father, and inveſted him with the Diadem: ſo may King <hi>Charles</hi> anſwer <hi>Spain,</hi> that therefore God will make him mighty in his Provinces, in deſpight of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:184920:7"/> malignant oppoſition, and great <hi>Britain</hi> ſhall not be onely able to ſtand firme, like an impregnable Rock in all honor, riches, &amp; proſperity: but of ſufficiency to protect diſtreſſed neighbours, and recover un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate and ſurrepted Provinces. Therefore away yee <hi>Frieſts</hi> and <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> packe hence for your lives; and let me not heare any further of your daring impoſtures, and you that will remaine Papiſts, and with the <hi>Adder</hi> ſtoppe your eares, that charme the <hi>Charmer</hi> never ſo cunningly, he ſhall not prevaile to remove you, take heed and be warned, that you live modeſtly in your wilfulneſſe, neither daring to breake our <hi>Statutes</hi> againſt thoſe Locuſts of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor to inſult your ſelves, or be offenſive to any ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill converſation, by thewrong defence and ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of <hi>Romes</hi> corrupted <hi>Doctrine.</hi> For I proteſt unto you by the faith of a Religious King, I take a pleaſure in hearing, what God ſaid to <hi>Abraham:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Geneſis 18.19</note> For I know him, that he will command his children, and his houſhold after him, and they ſhall keepe the way of the Lord to doe juſtice and judgement, that the Lord may bring upon <hi>Abraham</hi> that which he hath ſpoken unto him: And therefore as I am Gods ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute in the ſupreame royalty, ſo will I be his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument in the practiſe of this <hi>Reformation,</hi> neither ſuffring any Papiſt whatſoever, to have the uſe of Idolatrous maſſes, nor to bring up their owne chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the <hi>Cimmerian</hi> darkneſſe of ignorance, and diveliſh devotion: For the Apoſtle tells us plainely, <note place="margin">Coloſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that the tormenting of the body, worſhipping of Angels, obſerving of Dayes, and many fooliſh hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliations, likewiſe denying of lawful <hi>marriage,</hi> and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:184920:8"/> forbidding of meates, and celebrating of ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous times, are all the <hi>doctrines</hi> of the Divell: and is not this joy to <hi>great Britaine,</hi> and how are our hearts cheered, as you read of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that in the time of <hi>Salomon</hi> rejoyced with one another, and made merry eating and drinking under their owne Vines?</p>
            <p>Thus ſhall we ſee the backes of our <hi>adverſaries,</hi> and by Gods ſpeciall favour and grace the baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Ieſuites:</hi> But yee Magiſtrates of the Common wealth, let them not imitate the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> in this, to rob the <hi>Egyptians</hi> in their departure out of <hi>Egypt?</hi> Let them not export our treaſures, nor enrich other Countries with our ſpoyles: Let not your Ladies beſtow their jewels and ornaments up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them: For though they could be contented to love them with gratuities and preſents, yet muſt the Common wealth reſerve ſome ſecrets of State, not to be impoveriſhed by the laviſh gifts of thoſe, that underſtand not the Myſtery of carying wealth out of the Land, or conſuming our ſilver in trifles, let none of their houſes be furniſhed with thoſe rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants of gew-gawes, wherein the ancient idolaters excelled them in be decking their idols, <hi>I mean their medales, crucifixes, relickes of Saints, the Wood of the Croſſe, the milke of our Lady, and a thouſand ſuch like trumperies fit for nothing but toyes to play with all, as Apes doe with Nut ſhells:</hi> For as you read how the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were tainted with the groſſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition of <hi>Egypt:</hi> ſo muſt needs the tender hearts of your women be captivated with the reſervation of theſe things: Let your Purſevants and Officers
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:184920:8"/> a Gods name be the <hi>reſearchers</hi> of ſuſpected places, that the very children, which as yet, know no harm, may be ſent to the Schooles of the children of the Prophets, and by that meanes learne to live in the feare of God, and dye in his favour: Let the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent men be diſarmed a Gods name, not to give them cauſe to thinke the better of themſelves, as if they were to be feared, or reputed dangerous and poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke: but as you take knives and other hurtfull things from madde men to prevent miſchiefe, that they neyther endanger others, nor themſelves: In a word, <hi>let all good orders be obſerved, and a faſhionable body of a religious Common wealth erected, that his Majeſties perſon may be ſecured, the Prince, and the reſt of that Royall iſſue protected and pleaſed,</hi> the honeſt neighbours ſublevated with care and diligence, the whole Iland flouriſhing with proſperity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, the poore releeved, the trades reſtored, the City repayred, the Marchant countenanced, the Souldiers eſteemed, the Clergy-man beloved, the well deſerving reverence, the weake ſupported, the obſtinate finner puniſhed, the offender through frailty remitted, and all juſtifiable actions practiſed to the glory of God, and comfort of our owne ſoules.</p>
            <p>Then if there be cauſe of <hi>warre,</hi> and ſo ſucceſſe fallen, <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Iſraell</hi> ſhall ſing a ſong of Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph to the Lord, and <hi>Miriam</hi> the Propheteſſe ſhall take a <hi>Timbrell</hi> in her hand, and all the women goe after her with <hi>Timbrels</hi> and Dances: Then if there be the flouriſhes of peace, and that <hi>Salomon</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:184920:9"/> hath finiſhed the Temple of God, and his owne houſe, <note place="margin">1 King 3.22.9</note> he will preſent himſelfe before the <hi>Lord,</hi> and kneele to his <hi>prayers,</hi> ſpredding forth his hands to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Heaven: And then to conclude both in <hi>warre</hi> and peace ſhall <hi>great Britaine</hi> confeſſe to the <hi>Lord.</hi> What is man, that thou ſhouldſt thinke upon him, or the ſonne of man, that thou wilt remember him? And ſo prayſe the <hi>Lord</hi> in his Sanctuary, <hi>and in the firmament of his power: praiſe him in his mighty acts, and according to the excellency of his greatneſſe, praiſe him for thinking vpon vs, even in this particular of ſuppreſſing Papiſtry, and baniſhing the Prieſts and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will meddle with no matter of State, nor ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture traducing for ſelfe love, or adviſing others wiſer then my ſelfe, but keepe cloſe to the ſhore of this one ſpeciall obſervation: <hi>Let the adverſaries of Religion ſay what they can to accuſe a Proteſtant of one murther,</hi> whereas God and the world knowes, that not onely the turbulencies of <hi>Europe</hi> have beene blowne up with <hi>Popiſh breath, and ſufflation of Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian Cardinals:</hi> but the fearefull ſlaughters of <hi>Princes</hi> have beene andaciouſly proſecuted, eyther by <hi>Friers</hi> and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> or ſuch inſtruments, whom the peſtilent Ieſuites have ſeduced: what ſtate then in the world <hi>(eſpecially our reformed Churches) if there were no other cauſe then this affrighting, would endure them in the government,</hi> and therefore now this muſt needs be a happineſſe to <hi>England,</hi> that at this inſtant ſuch a mercy floweth towards us, as a <hi>Proclamation</hi> againſt them.</p>
            <p>How <hi>Geneva</hi> hath continued, and groaned under
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:184920:9"/> the preſſure of many difficulties, yea, endured divers aſſaults of whole Armies, and volleies of ſhot, from the mounted Cannons againſt her; and yet was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any attempt made upon the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and her adveiſaries by her procurement, or ſuggeſtion, is well knowne to the world.</p>
            <p>In all thoſe bloody maſſacres of <hi>France,</hi> and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of the civill <hi>warres</hi> there, what one miſchiefe was ever conceived againſt the perſons of their Kings, by any <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and who but <hi>Papiſts</hi> durſt lay hands on the Lords Annoynted? In that fiery tryall in the dayes of Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> when the rages of Papiſts made them more furious, then a Beare robbed of her Whelpes: What one Proteſtant ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped out of the circle of obedience, to put her in ſuſpition of her life, yea it is well knowne, that the Proteſtants of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> advanced her to the Crowne though they were the firſt that felt the effect of her ingratitude. In all the troubles of <hi>Germany,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions upon the free Cities, how ſecurely did the <hi>Emperours</hi> goe on concerning their owne perſons, and when did you read of a Pope ſlaine, but as they poyſoned one another. I will name but one thing in the Low-Countries, and that is the pride and cruelty of the Duke of <hi>Alva;</hi> ſo that if ever an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe might have been made for taking away a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants life, it might here in ſome action or other, have received a juſtifiable forme, and yet <hi>Alva</hi> lived with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out touch, and practiſed all manner of wickedneſſe without controule: whereas on the contrary ſide in theſe Countries formerly mentioned, there hath bin
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:184920:10"/> a 1000 ſeverall murthers committed upon the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of publicke and private perſons, or at leaſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted with reſolution to be actuated upon advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by Popiſh Prieſts, Ieſuites, and their Officials, and Miniſters: Is it not high time then to baniſh them our Common-wealth, or do as we have done (and ſo it ſhall be no new matter or deviſe of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment) even hang them up at Tyborne, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude them into the houſe of ſlaughter, where Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is predominant.</p>
            <p>Marke for Gods ſake, marke the ſecrets of good husbandry, he that means to till and manure a wod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ground, muſt leave no ſtumps within touch, leſt he break his plow in the labour, and ſee freſh ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as ſprigs to ſprout up to choake the Corne: the beſt way is to ſtocke up roote and tinde, and follow the picke-axe with a ſpade, that the ground may be throughly ſearched indeede; and ſo muſt <hi>great Britaine</hi> do with this brood of Vipers, eyther pull out their ſtings, or chap them in peeces: For ſo were the Prieſts of <hi>Baal</hi> ſerved at ſeverall times, and in ſeverall places by <hi>Gedeon, Iohn, Elias, Ioſias,</hi> and other good <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Princes:</hi> but ſeeing this good beginning of our gracious and iudicious King, in quenching the ſmoake of theſe fire-brands, which in time would eyther have blinded our eyes, or put them cleane out, hath cheered our hearts, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the balme of <hi>Gilead</hi> into our wounds, let him have the glory of his owne handy-worke, and <hi>great Britaine</hi> the joy, and ſo both he, <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> and every true Chriſtian retribute all poſſible thankes to the ancient of dayes, whoſe haires are as white as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:184920:10"/> wooll, and dyes as a flame of fire; and to the voyce that commandeth us out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> leſt we be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed in her abominations: For <hi>Babylon is fallen, is fallen, that great City, becauſe ſhe made all the Nations drinke of the Wine of the wrath of her Fornication.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
